The sky is blossoming with stars,
The evening's wreathing lights.
Oh, the nights, Donetsk nights,
years of my youth.
What do you want?
FLOWER ON A STONE
Oleksandr Dovzhenko
Kyiv Film Studio
Why did you do this?
I couldn't do in other way.
I'm conscious again.
Sorry...
Fine, we'll talk later.
Now go to bed, take a rest.
Don't go, doctor!
Stay.
Let's come up, doctor.
Birds...
Can you hear?
- Doctor?
- What?
Do you know, these trees...
are just one year old?
I don't, I'm... a newcomer.
- Then you do not know how things began.
- No.
The new city will arise here
despite arrogant neighbour!
Komsomolska mine will be built here
Hop Out, Everyone!
Just look!
Smile!
Like it?!
- What about speeches, orchestra?
- Where will we receive mail?
Liuda, where will I live with my wife?
- Hey! They are coming!
- Coming!
Donetsk salutation
to respected Komsomol!
Salute!
- Who are you?
- Let me introduce!
Hryhorii Hryva. Mine drifter.
You drifted a lot, yeah?
If following you - to the world's end!
"Be Aware of blue eyes and
black brows", - father warned.
You had to listen to your father!
Meteoric decision...
Today we dance.
Tomorrow go to restaurant
to solidify relations.
After tomorrow we get married.
And you move to my flat
as a legal wife!
What if I do not want to?
- Do you know who speaks to you?
- Who?
He's the beauty and pride of Donbas!
Hryhorii Hryva!
Let your beauty and pride... wait!
I will dance with him...
when he learns how to ask!
Are you gonna teach me?
Listen... She’s not alone here.
- I see nobody.
- You'd better do.
They are coming! Coming!
Hey! Why are you nipping off?
Wait! Let’s go to the restaurant!
Look! More fiancés are coming!
These ones are richer! Driving Volga!
- Good morning!
- Greetings!
- Who are you?
- Me?
I’m... future boss...
of the future mine.
- Comrade Varchenko?
- Pavlo Fedorovych.
And I’m Komsomol leader.
That’s might.
Where blue mountains are...
the Carpathian mountains,
fog floats over the valleys...
You’ll go to the Donbas,
to be building the mine...
It will be hard there, but...
in the hardness souls are reaching for God...
You’ll work hard, become a role model,
find friends - reliable, faithful.
I will come in a year.
We’ll get together brothers, sisters...
organise big family...
and glorify God.
I will glorify God here and
ask for His mercy...
- No-no-no, it is needed there.
- And here.
- Khrystyna...
- I can’t!
Khrystyna.
Hryva?
Why are you here?
I’m dreaming.
Dreaming? What about?
Who wants to know everything,
will age quickly,
mademoiselle Komsomol lead.
Come inside the tent! Let’s dance!
You invite me.
But you’ll dance with me.
Me only.
Is it your rule?
My rule.
Liuda Kharko, Liuda!
Liuda! Take it! Letter for you!
It’s got wet, sorry!
A newspaper, a magazine!
Oh, parcel for Dzhaparidze. Dzhaparidze!
From home...
Khrystyna...
Cross the doorstep of my home.
I was waiting for you
impatiently, dear sister.
Enter my house and lift with us
your soul towards God.
From your father? Thank you.
Come in, sister, come in.
From now on this house is your house.
Our souls are always opened for you,
as the doors of my house.
Sit.
In time of need...
when a heavy stone
is on your friends’ souls...
remind them of God.
In this house they will always find
solace, peace and love.
God is love.
We get closer to God through soul,
not through the cross...
God is love.
Come in, dear sister.
- "How the Steel Was Tempered".
- Well, fine.
- "Gadfly" by Voynich.
- My favorite book!
Here...
Please.
I can offer you some
anti-religious literature.
Of sectarians, Jehovah’s Witnesses.
About orthodox clerics.
I would say these people are worse
than your cardinal Montanelli.
Clerics say a lot of God,
but forget about the human soul.
But human soul is such
a complex instrument.
Don't you have a book
about Pentecostals?
Comrade Varchenko, just in time!
Remarque is waiting for you.
Here you are.
Thanks. So, don’t you have
this kind of book?
Sadly, no.
Nevertheless, in the encyclopaedia...
volume 38, page 399...
There is nothing essential
about sectarians.
Sectarians in Islam, in Buddhism...
It's history... But I'm preoccupied
with nowadays.
Pentecostals.
Well, what I would say:
it's a small, unremarkable sect.
No wonder, nobody is writing.
Pavlo Fedorovych!
Comrade Zabroda, obviously,
learnt this issue deeply.
Let’s ask him to make a lecture?
You try, make a deal.
Come on, what a lecturer am I?
I even be ashamed
to speak to the audience.
Dare to try.
Thanks for your regard,
but this job's not for me.
Ventilation is so poor here.
I'd better find a new space for you.
Not for you. For Pentecos... Ugh!
For the book storage.
Unload faster!
- Your books.
- Thanks.
- Have you ever been in the mine?
- No. Take me, Pavlo Fedorovych!
Sit.
Some Komsomol leader you are...
Come again, Pavlo Fedorovych.
We can make a subscription.
- Look, Komsomol, what mine is.
- Is it your first time?
- An actress?
- Even worse.
- A journalist!
- Guess again!
- Pavlo Fedorovych, can I go there?
- Go ahead.
Just be careful.
- Vasia!
- Come on!
Watch, where are you going!
- Komsomol!
- Hello!
- Staring here?
- Yes!
- Can I bring our fellows here?
- Not all at once.
- Foreman, what's going on?
- It’s all right!
- It seemed the hammer has fallen!
- Thank you, Pavlo Fedorovych.
- Thank to the master.
Did you like it?
A bit scary first.
And then I used to.
- Can I bring the guys here?
- Sure, you can.
But not all of them at once.
- Well, I got to go...
- Maybe, tea?
No, I’m in a hurry.
Well, you're in charge now...
Tomorrow I’ll bring
all the lads to the mine.
One will go to the mine,
but another... to the sect.
Do you know such people?
- I know...
- You know who?
- What're you gonna do?
I’ve... sent a letter to her father.
Well-well. Made a favour...
for the old man.
But he’s a sectarian himself!
Then...
Then I’ll chew her out at the meeting!
I’ll chew her out!
They promise her love
and peace in their house.
And you want to scold her...
Liuda... What time are you living in?
Pardon?
- Welcome.
- Pasha.
- Ordered yet?
- Two homemade noodle soups.
Shakespeare.
Sonnets.
Tonia! Two flasks and my usual appetizer!
Okay.
Your usual appetizer?
- You're like merchant Stroganov.
- Yes.
My usual appetizer.
Appetizer of Hryva the drifter.
- Would you mind?
- No!
Here you are, to your health
and arrival to the Donbas!
I mean you, Komsomol leader.
Too good for it?
- Let's go, Liuda.
- Where do you go?
Here you are, please.
- Please.
- Thanks.
Here are your homemade noodle soups.
Many thanks.
But you... we’ll have a special talk.
Give us Spirit, God!
- Glory to Jesus.
- Glory forever.
Give us Spirit, God.
You, come here.
Come, don't be afraid.
New series of nuclear explosions
was conducted by the USA
near Christmas Island.
This act stressed again...
What's the hell? Beep!
Arsen and Hryva...
Well, you fight, fight.
Let's see, who’s stronger.
I sacrificed two sons to the war.
So that you, two lads,
could maim each other?
Is that it?
Get in the car, Arsen.
And you, Hryva, leave.
- What’s the business between you?
- Pavlo Fedorovych...
What should I do, Pavlo Fedorovych?
- She's a sectarian.
- Who’s a sectarian?
Khrystyna... Khrystyna Ravliuk!
Why do you hang with her?
I love her.
Can you understand, I love.
Tell her about it.
I love you above all!
Love you more than life,
more than sun!
You shouldn't love me!
I beg you!
- I Love!
- No!
Khrystyna! Where are you going, stop!
Khrystyna!
No! No!
Lord!
(whisper) More than life...
I love you...
I love you!
I’m sectarian! I believe in God
and love Him more than life!
You’ve got to know
everything about me.
I know everything about you.
- You know?
- Yes.
- I know...
- And?...
And love me as I am?
I love...
My darling... Beloved...
Join my sect!
And I’ll be your wife!
Faithful and devoted.
Like in God’s face.
I’m waiting for the answer.
You don’t love me.
Fine. Come on.
Let him in.
Greetings.
Brothers and sisters!
Come in.
Brothers and sisters.
Today when we make
our modest offerings...
to God...
Him, the Most High, has brought
to our family a new brother.
Come here, my brother.
- What’s your name?
- Arsen Zahornyi.
Brother Arsen.
God has brought you to us
in a solemn moment.
- It’s a sign of goodness.
- Thanks.
And now, brothers and sisters,
let ask God
with our infinite love,
and endless devotion,
He accepted from us
our modest offerings.
- Our modest offerings!
- Our modest offerings...
Modest offerings.
Apostle Paul says to us:
The Bible (published in New York):
"Having livelihood and clothes,
let be satisfied with these.
But who wants to get rich
fall into temptation and netting.
As the root for all evil
is love of money".
Brothers and sisters!
- God accepted all our offerings.
- Oh God!
Truth has been revealed for me...
from our new brother.
God craves faith.
Are you ready to give God...
- ...a drop of blood?
- You mean?
Finger of your hand,
which is closer to the heart,
has to be laid under a sacral axe.
Think until the morning.
If you came to us with clear soul,
your faith brings you here again.
And gives drop of blood to God.
Oh God!
- I’m scared, Arsen. I’m scared.
- Be calm, Khrystyna.
Calm.
Chmykh!
- Who is he, this Zahornyi?
- Member of the Komsomol committee!
An intellectual.
- Do you think faith brought him here?
- No.
- What does he want here?
- I don’t know.
I would surprise him
with a single drop of blood.
I’m afraid he won’t come again.
I’ve seen fear in his eyes.
Oh my, weakling.
I will ask God not to accept
from you this sacrifice.
Khrystyna, easy, don’t think of it.
Khrystyna! Buy it, don’t hesitate.
- Hrysha! Which one? I’m confused.
- Choose yourself.
Evening suit, the one in the window.
Size 52. Tall.
Khrystyna, wait a moment.
- Sister! Why did your faith stagger?
- I love him.
God is love. But yours
is not love, but sin!
I love him!
Drive the devil away, sister. Wake up!
Otherwise God will judge you and him, both.
Get back to your
brothers and sisters!
Ministry of Culture of the UkrSSR
Donetsk Regional Museum
Kids, make a circle!
Do not touch the exhibits,
do not ask questions.
Well, this part of the museum
is dedicated to the Donbas history
Peter the Great issued a decree in 1723.
"To the Dnipro river,
and its tributaries,
to explore and search for black coal
- assign deacon Kapustin".
And now we move to the section
"Takeover in Donbas".
Lenin addressed miners:
"Coal is a true bread for the industry".
Flower... Stiopa, come here!
Flower on a stone.
We are saying goodbye,
getting ready to go,
happier and more beautiful,
the world has ever known.
Friends, we're going,
and promise in our hearts,
that we'll stay
seventeen forever.
- Baraniuk. Come here.
- What?
By the rule
we got to celebrate victory.
It’s an idea! Fellas, come here!
- So, we have to organize.
- Don't worry.
We did it!
- Come on.
- Sure!
- Who made all the guys drunk?
- I’ve treated them.
Me.
Following old miner’s tradition.
Just look.
The guys won the banner,
they worked as devils -
and nobody rewarded them
even a drink.
32 workers
didn’t come to work today!
32? Losers!
As you see, we’ve come.
Mademoiselle Komsomol leader
is mourning the authority she's lost.
Where did you come from?
You’re all such a waste and
belong to the mine dump.
To the mine dump!
Hrysha, come on.
Why are you upset?
It’s... a Komsomol media.
- Get used to self-criticism.
- Shut up!
Hrysha, where are you going?
To the spoil tip
means to the spoil tip!
Hrysha? Where you go?
Hrysha!
Hry...
Guys, over here!
- What’s up?
- Look, it’s Hryva!
- Let's take him to the hostel.
- Go ahead! One, two, heave.
Who’s there?
- Serhii? What’s up?
- Excuse me.
Can you give us a needle and black thread?
- The jacket was torn...
- Let me see.
Come back in an hour.
Maybe, I’ll bring it myself, fine?
Fine, thanks.
- Serhii? Did anybody fight?
- No.
My honest Komsomol word - no!
Well, and I see rock
under the glass.
300.000 years old!
And an imprint on it - the flower.
I’ll find such a rock and send it
to the village. Let them enjoy!
Well, fine, turn off the light.
Let’s sleep.
Year 1723. Kapustin.
Russian. Named Hryshka.
He was the first who discovered
black coal in the Donetsk steppe.
He should have been commemorated
in the book of miners’ glory!
But they’ve forgotten...
Not fair.
Mit’ka, are you asleep? Hey!
On January 26, this year
in the funeral day of the leader
to USSR Council of people's commissars
Vladimir Lenin...
the mines...
will not work...
- Good morning, aunt Dasha!
- Good morning, Liudochka!
Wipe the feet.
- Greetings, Pavlo Fedorovych.
- Greetings.
- Pouring the flowers.
- They also want to drink.
- Don’t be surprised, Pavlo Fedorovych.
- Nothing to surprise. Everything is clear.
- Really? Do you know, why I'm here?
- Already know.
No, you can’t know this.
Don’t even try to show sagacity.
- Take me to work in the mine.
- What?
You’ve said you know everything!
No, I didn't know this...
Why do you need it?
- Is it easier to make lads drunk?
- I’m going to work here!
Well... I’m not against.
But you know, I’m a chief only.
There are...
Communist Party head, Komsomol...
- Who?
- Komsomol lead, for example.
We build Komsomolska mine here.
She must be asked.
- Pavlo Fedorovych! Don’t!
- Why ‘don’t’?
- Don’t!
- We should.
Look, how signaling works.
Three knocks - Komsomol lead comes.
Four knocks - accountant appears.
- Did you call, Pavlo Fedorovych?
- Called. Need your advise.
Here is Hrysha Hryva...
He‘s hiring to our mine
as a tunneller.
- I do not hire!
- Quiet.
He came to be hired.
What do Komsomol think?
- Let’s hire?
- I think...
Let’s hire. With the only condition.
Interesting! What conditions
can you demand for?
Two times. Chief engineer is calling.
- You talk here...
- Pavlo Fedorovych.
- Just a moment!
- Pavlo Fedorovych!
Pardon.
For good memories.
What's this?
Why are you like this?
Why are you so messed up?
Brilliant work - and drinking!
What’s this? How to understand this?
I love you.
Don’t you dare to speak of love!
Do you hear? Don’t!
So what?
Shell we hire
Hryhorii Hryva to the mine?
Your decision, Pavlo Fedorovych.
Hryva. Hryva!
What's this?
- It’s a keepsake...
- Give it here.
Just look.
A flower.
300.000 years old.
Ah, Liuda...
Hryva is a poet.
But you didn't got it.
Rise up on your toes...
Hands to the side and down.
Stand the full feet.
Stretch.
- Are they sleeping?
- Returned from the nightshift.
Mummy! Do you know these guys?
Sure, each of them.
He’s from Poltava. Serhii Marchenko.
Writer, composes poetry.
And that one - with an accent,
dark-haired...
he is from amateur activity.
Dances on the tiptoes.
And there... chubby guy.
Koval’. Almost a child.
Dispatcher calling the foreman.
- Serhii Marchenko.
- Me.
- Black-haired, dancing
the tiptoes - who's the one?
Dzhaparidze?
- Dzhaparidze.
- Me!
- Baraniuk Hennadii.
- Kusenko.
- Me!
- Potapov.
- Koval’.
- Me.
What a gang! The hottest!
What a gang! Nothing to say.
Fine, go away!
It’s your foreman.
- Hryhorii Hryva, tunneler.
- Pavlo Fedorovych...
How many of you per pound, guys?
- Thank you, Pavlo Fedorovych...
- Pavlo Fedorovych!
Odesa is calling.
- It’s unfair.
- What’s unfair?
What kind of men did you give him?
Do you hear? All are laughing.
Let’s see.
Hold on, it’s dark in the mine!
Can you differ coal and rock?
Laughing? Well-well...
Come on, guys.
Bring you some mush, eh?
Guys, I will tell... the thing.
All the world’s beauty
comes from human.
Gagarin raised to cosmos.
And us - under the ground.
So it means...
that all the world’s beauty...
comes from us, bros.
The thing is to believe
in your own force.
An then... Everything will be fine then.
Hryva will be pushed around!
Stop talking! Better help Arsen!
Why me?
It’s again from Hryva!
- Is it again by accident?
- They are shooting the rats!
Stop chattering! Back to work!
- Turn on!
- Aye!
Hrysha, how did you
overrun us in a whole cycle?
Hear badly, say louder!
How did you manage
to overrun us in a whole cycle?
- How do you know?
- We’ve heard, when you undermined.
Guys!
Hear? They want our secrets.
Dude, perhaps you
want your back washed?
- Did you forget to laugh?
- Forgot!
Hrysha! Hrysha...
Where have you been lost?
Hrysha, let’s go?
- For clearness.
- Piss off...
- Guardian angel...
- What’s wrong?
- Just go your way!
What’s up? Hrysha? Wait!
Why are you cocky?
You’ve got fellas!
Just wait! We’ll meet again!
Come in.
Hryva? Come in.
- How are you?
- Fine, I’ve just dropped in...
- Sorry, am I bothering?
- No-no, sit.
Stendhal. "Red and Black".
You have to read it.
I watched the film.
Good fellow.
Can’t catch the second series.
Listen, Hryva.
- Why don’t you apply for the apartment?
- Why do I need it?
Mother is in the village.
Father...
died...
Write.
I apply to provide me
with living space...
...on the territory
of Dobryi Shliakh village.
Family members:
Mother... dependent...
- What’s her name?
- Mariia Mykolaivna.
Sign.
Here we are. Now I’ll walk through
the village with a pink lamp-shade.
- Why the pink one?
- I didn’t see another.
Mark 2 for the audition.
Re-write.
- "You" in capital letter.
- Come on.
Hey, come on!
Guest in the house,
a host out of house.
Turn on!
Happy housewarming!
Daddy!
Oh my God!
- Are you my daughter?!
- Don’t worry, I’ll wash.
Foreman, don’t worry!
He’s her father!
I’m not worrying.
No reason to worry.
Let’s have lunch now.
And the concert in the evening.
Listen, Liudochka.
I’ve come not for long.
I leave today. We need to talk.
- Liuda?
- What do you want?
- Hello.
- We go to bosses and need a car.
- Go to the dispatcher, I agreed yet.
Go ahead! Daddy, go to that house,
I will come up, ok?
Hey, look…
When are you going home?
Daddy, do you think it’s possible?
Kiss mom,
I'll come on vacations soon.
- Alone?
- Don’t worry, alone!
You better be, don’t linger.
- Hold the milk, please!
- Sure. Bye.
Come, we’re waiting.
Lets start
the "Holy Gifts" concert!
Dear, where are you pulling me?
Where are you pulling me?
God, accept our offerings!
- Offer!
Why did you do all this stuff?
Why?! It’s not true!
Stop! It’s not true!
- Chmykh!
- What?
- Well, what’s going on there?
- Satire.
- You look very alike.
- Hey-hey!
It’s Arsen’s pranks...
How is Khrystyna?
Differently.
- Well, act. Understand?
- Understand!
Just carefully.
Khrystyna!
Khrystyna, where do you go?
- Where?
- Don’t you follow me...
You do not know,
how things can end up.
Brother! Save me, my brother!
I’ve trusted them, but they deride us.
They do not understand us.
My sister...
I haven’t seen you
for so long, my dear.
- Forgive me! Forgive!
- God forgives you.
If only you’ve returned
truly and forever in your heart...
- ...to God.
- I’ve returned.
- I’ve returned for all my life.
- Thank you, thank you, sister.
- You’ll be my wife...
- Wife?!
- You’ll be!
- Give your sacred blessing, father.
- Daddy...
- Bless you.
- Daddy, are you here?
- Bless you forever.
- Wife...
- Wife.
You are my wife now.
Father’s blessing is sacral.
- How can it be?
- Sacral and inviolable.
Daddy! What happiness
are you talking about?
Daddy...
What happiness?
Come with me.
Oh Dear!
- And You see all these!
- Khrystyna!
- Come to yourself, sister!
- Shut up!
Arsen Zahornyi?
- Let’s go.
- Where?
We have to talk.
Let’s go.
Stop, stop! Stop, Hrysha, hurry up!
They are hitting Arsen now, come on!
In Ural, autonomous republics
of the middle and bottom Volga regions
there is low cloud and warm weather.
In the north-west region
of the USSR European territory...
...in Belarus and bigger part of Ukraine
it is warm without fallouts.
...in the east of the central part
of European territory of the Union...
...termination of the fallouts
is expected,..
...but rains are expected
in the east of central part
and northern regions of Ukraine.
Rest of the terrain in Ukraine,
Moldova, Crimean sea coast...
Hrysha!
Comrade Varchenko, good afternoon!
You’ve predicted it.
You see? They are breaking.
Pavlo Fedorovych, did you hear, what
happened in the eve, some confusion?
- Stop fooling, Zabroda.
- What do you mean?
Your beliefs - it's your business.
But when you destroy human souls -
our business begins! Go!
What do you mean?
- Well...
- Wow! What’s this?
This?
At night in the vault!
- Uncle Pasha?
- What?
I can't get a note here.
Please show me.
Ugh you, dudes.
Pasha Chmykh... does the best.
Listen.
And now... continue playing with joy...
and come with us to the police!
Wha-a-at?
- Come on, guys!
- Play!
Play with joy.
- More joy, more!
- Go ahead.
Go-go!
It seems... everything happened
just tomorrow.
- What were you afraid of?
- Presbyter.
But we are stronger
than him, Khrystyna.
- What are you saying?
- Stronger.
There is no God in the sky,
believe me.
- Why are you here?
- To see him?
- Yes, him.
- Pass, please. Milk.
Milk?
Where you’ve gone?
Doctor! Welcome to my housewarming!
Thanks. I’ll come.
I was asked to pass you milk.
- Go...
- Fresh.
Drink immediately, until it is warm.
I thought you're inviting doctor...
to the wedding.
You just drink, in small drinks,
don’t hurry, don’t gulp...
Nurse, we’re just for a minute,
please, please!
- Hi!
Here. M-i-l-k.
Screenplay Vadym Sobko
Film director Sergei Parajanov
Cameramen Serhii Revenko, Lev Shtyfanov
Artistic director Mykhailo Rakovskyi
Costume design Olha Yablonska
Makeup Volodymyr Shykin
Second directors Liudmyla Dzenkevych,
Volodymyr Parkhomenko
Assistant director Zh. Chaika
Composer Ihor Shamo
Sound engineer Arkadii Lupal
Editing Marfa Ponomarenko
Production executive R. Korol
Lyrics Dmytro Lutsenko, L. Smyrnova
State Symphony Orchestra of the UkrSSR,
conductor Veniamin Tolba
Production management N. Vaintrob
CAST:
Varchenko - Borys Dmokhovskyi
Hryva - Hryhorii Karpov
Liuda - Liudmyla Cherepanova
Khrystyna - Inna Kyryliuk (Burduchenko)
Zahornyi - Heorhii Yepifantsev
Zabroda - Mykhailo Nazvanov
Chmykh - Dmytro Franko
Mineworkers of Donetsk region